INDRJEET KUMAR

2: 8147978847

BACKGROUND

Experienced professional with 18+ years in the information technology industry has a wide range of experience providing Architecture, Project Management, Account management, Coding, Development, Documentation, Testing & Implementing Business Technology using the Agile and Scrum.

EXPERIENCE SNAPSHOT



IAVA~ TECHNOLOGY

INDUSTRY

- BFSI
- Telecom
- Trading
- Utilities
- Life Science
- Energy

TECHNICAL SPECIALIZATION

- Business-to-Business Solution Design
- Business-to-Consumer solution design
- · Database Design

CERTIFICATIONS

- Java
- Big Data & Hadoop

TRAINING

- AWS, Python
- Kafka
- Micro Service
- Docker, Kubernetes
- DevOps (CI/CD)
- Rest, gRPC
- Big Data & Hadoop
- GoF & J2EE Design Patterns
- Spring, Spring Boot
- NoSQL, HBase, Cassandra

- Subject matter expert (SME) in Python, AWS, S3, Glue, IAM, Redshift, EMR, ECS, ELB, RDS, Route53, Firehose, Athena, Terraform, Cloudtail CloudWatch, Cloud Formation, Auto Scaling, UNIX, Linux & Database
- Subject matter expert (SME) in **Docker**, **Kubernetes** & **DevOps** (CI/CD).
- Subject matter expert (SME) in Kafka Core, Kafka Stream, Kafka Connect, Kafka KSQL and Kafka Pipeline.
- Very good knowledge on the **Distributed System**, **Security**, **Scalability**, **Reliability**, **Optimization** and **Performance**.
- Strong programming skills in designing and implementation of multi-tier applications using Scala, Spark, Java, J2EE, Struts, JavaScript, AJAX, jQuery, JSON, Rest, gRPC, Unix, Linux, Oracle, Weblogic, Autosys and Remedy.
- Excellent Knowledge of **Spring Boot** and **Micro services**.
- Excellent knowledge of **Hadoop architecture** and various components such as **HDFS**, **MapReduce**, **Hive**, **Pig**, **Zookeeper**, **Spark** and **HBase** programming paradigm.
- Proficient in **Leading and Mentoring Individuals** to leverage productivity.
- Strong Interpersonal and Communication Skills, Enthusiastic and Self-Driven with a high degree of commitment
- Multi-Tasking attitude and ability to motivate the team members as well as extensive knowledge of advanced technical tools and applications
- Exposure to Cross Cultural work environment in **USA** and **UK**.
- Worked and **managed teams** in varied work culture environments.
- Passable knowledge of **German**.
- Developed curricula and taught AWS, Kafka, Docker, Spring, Hibernate, UNIX and Design Patterns.
- Member of the Computer Science of India (CSI).
- **© Big Data** and **Hadoop** certification from **Edupristine** and **Simplilearn**.
- Smart working, Self-starter with excellent analytical, problem-solving, and communication
- Deep Logical Thinking with an eye for Detail and Design.

EXPERIENCE

Company: Marlabs Client: SiriusXM (Feb/2020 - To-Date)

Product: https://www.siriusxm.com/

- SiriusXM is a satellite and streaming audio entertainment company. SiriusXM's platforms collectively reach more than 900 million listeners across all categories of digital audio music, sports, talk, and podcasts
- As a technical architect responsibility include Architecture Document, Detailed Design Documents, Business Flow Documents, Interface Document, Security Document, Application code Assessment Documents.
- Working on multiple Kafka data pipeline and Kafka consumer such as Provisioning, Linking, Synacor, Feature, SMS RTPT, Akamai, Gup and Dynamic Partition.
- Create the schema using the Crawler.
- Use the data lake to access the data using the Redshift and Athena.
- Lead the technical team and mentored Team Lead, Developers, Tester and Agile Team.
- Implementation of Agile methodology

Technical Environment:

Kafka, Kafka Consumer, Docker, Python, Java 8, AWS, Spark, Crawler, CloudTrail, Athena, Red shift, Crawler, Dynamic Partition, EMR, EC2, Glue, S3, IAM, Policy, Route53, CloudWatch, Cloud Formation, Auto Scaling, Terraform, Tidal, Infogix control, Rest, DevOps (CI/CD), BitBucket, Linux, Eclipse, Maven, UML & Agile

Company: Marlabs Client: West corporation (Feb/2020 Dec/2021)

Product: https://www.westuc.com/en-us/digital-media-services/webcast-pro

- Webcast Pro product provides solutions to Broadcast Interactive Presentations and delivers crystal clear audio, video, and slides for an unmatched attendee experience without requiring special hardware or software, for audiences everywhere: internal, external, local, or global.
- Working on the many vertical applications such as Portal, channels, Reports, webcast player, Batch Server, video Transcoders, Reports and CDN Integration. has been develop using the EJB and JPA.
- Created a timer service using the EJB.
- As a technical architect responsibility include Architecture document, Detailed Design documents, Business Flow documents, Interface document, Security Document, Application code Assessment documents.
- Develop the application in the AWS to process the data
- Lead the technical team and mentored Team Lead, Developers, Agile Team, and Tester.
- Implementation of agile methodology

Technical Environment:

Python, Java 8, AWS, Lambda, CloudTrail, Athena, Red shift, Crawler, EMR, Ec2, Glue, S3, IAM, Policy, EJB3, Route53, CloudWatch, Cloud Formation, Auto Scaling, JPA, Elastic Search, Neo4j, Hazel cast, Rest, DevOps (CI/CD), BitBucket, Linux, Eclipse, Maven, Ant, UML, Oracle, Oracle Datawarehouse, Linux, jUnit, Mockito, Power mock, Swagger, White source & Agile

Company: United Technologies Client: United Technology (Jan/2018 – Dec 2019)

URL: https://www.utc.com

A Cortix is an advanced Artificial Intelligence (AI) and Internet of things (IOT) platform to provide analytics-driven energy management of building, site & equipment data.

Product: https://cortix.ai

- Working on the many vertical applications such as ADR, Cortix and Devops.
- As a technical architect responsibility include Architecture document, Detailed Design documents, Business Flow documents, Interface document, Security Document, Application code Assessment documents.
- Lead the technical team and mentored Team Lead, Developers, agile team & Tester.
- Implementation of agile methodology

Technical Environment:

Company: IBM Client: IBM (Sep/2016 – Aug/2017)

URL: https://www.ibm.com

- An ePolicy application is a web-based tool designed to facilitate the Digitation of policy document, base Document and Technical Specifications.
- Created a micro service for the technical specification document.
- As a technical architect responsibility include Architecture document, Detailed Design documents, Business Flow documents, Interface document, Security Document, Application code Assessment documents.
- Lead the technical team and mentored Team Lead, Developers and Tester.

Technical Environment:

Spring Boot, Micro Services, WebSphere, J2EE, Java, EJB, JMS, JavaScript, AJAX, Web Services (Rest), Struts, Spring, Free marker, Jasper Report, Apache POI, Sitemesh, Apache Common, Linux, Eclipse, Maven, Ant, UML, DB2 Database, Solaris, log4J, jUnit and Agile

Company: Yash Client: Sigma Aldrich (Dec/2015 Jul/2016)

URL: http://www.sigmaaldrich.com/

- An eNotebook software program designed to replace more traditional paper laboratory notebooks. Laboratory notebooks in general are used by scientists and technicians to document, store, retrieve, order, stockroom, education, library, research, Data Analytic, compliance and share fully electronic laboratory records in ways that meet all legal, Regulatory, Technical and Scientific requirements.
- Created a timer service using the EJB.

Technical Environment:

Jboss WildFly 8, Cassandra, ElasticSearch, J2EE, Java, EJB, JSF, jQuery, Quartz, JMS, Jackson, JavaScript, AJAX, Web Services (Rest), Linux, Eclipse, Maven, Ant, UML, Autosys, log4J, jUnit, Datastax Dev Center, Git, Docker and Agile

Company: UST Client: Dell (May/2015 – Sep/2015)

URL: http://www.dell.com/

- Involved in creating Architecture document, Detailed Design documents, Business Flow documents, Interface document, Security Document, Application code Assessment documents.
- Working on the many vertical applications such as MDM, BIL, DOMS, OFS, OPP, BOM and SKU and BTOA
- Lead the technical team and mentored Team Lead, Developers and Tester.

Technical Environment:

Company: CGI (05/09 - 01/2015)

• Fannie Mae

- **O** TD BANK NWCP
- Local Number Portability Order Fulfillment system
- Walled Garden Portal

Company: Eka Software Client: Noble Group (04/08 to 12/08)

Commodity Trading product

Company: Tech Mahindra Client: Alcatel (02/2004 - 04/2008)

- Traverse Product
- NOC (Network Operation Center and Service Order Processing System)
- LITE CRAFT (a lightweight EMS for DLC)

Company: Scandent Group (AUG 2002– FEB 2004)

- **EPIC** (Enterprise Program information Collaboration)
- SCANDASH
- **●** INFRASTRUCTURE AND CUSTOMER SUPPORT

EDUCATION

- B.E, PES Institute of Technology, Bangalore University, Computer Science
- First Rank in the department of Mathematics in graduation.

Certifications and Training

- Sun Certified Java Associates (SCJA).
- Sun Certified Enterprise Architect (SCEA).
- eMatrix Certified.